Guide to the Louise Glück Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Louise Glück papers
1950-2006
YCAL MSS 946
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
32.42
(31 boxes) + 8 art
Glück, Louise, 1943-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Wylie Agency on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 39: Restricted until 2050. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1950s-2005. II. Writings, 1950s-2006. III. Writings of Others, 1970s-2005. IV. Other Papers, 1950s-1990s. V. Artwork, 1958-1965. VI. Restricted Material.
Louise Glück
Louise Glück is an American poet. She was awarded the Pulitzer Prize for Poetry in 1993 for The Wild Iris, and the Bollingen Prize for Poetry in 2001. Glück served as the Poet Laureate Consultant in Poetry to the Library of Congress, 2003-2004.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, notebooks, writings of others, ephemera, photographs, and artwork documenting the life adn work of poet Louise Glück. Correspondence spans Glück's career and includes poets Steven Berg, Robert Pinsky, C. K. Williams, and others, as well as family correspondence. Writings include individual poems and drafts of collections including Ararat, The Wild Iris, Meadowlands, and Vita Nova. Writings of others include works by numerous writers including Steven Berg, Frank Bidart, Kathryn Davis, Robert Pinsky, Ellen Bryant Voigt, and C. K.Williams. Artwork includes oil paintings and watercolors by Louise Glück.
American literature -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Women authors; Oil paintings (visual works); Photographs; Watercolors (paintings); Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Bidart, Frank, 1939-; Berg, Steven, 1959-; Davis, Kathryn, 1946-; Glück, Louise, 1943-; Pinsky, Robert, 1940-; Voigt, Ellen Bryant, 1943-; Williams, C. K. (Charles Kenneth), 1936-2015
- Correspondence, 1950s-2005; Series I; 6; (6 boxes)
  - General correspondence, 1960s-2005
    - Althaus, Keith, circa 1972 (Box 14)
    - Ball, [Sally?], circa 1993 (Box 14)
    - Barbara [Guest?], undated (Box 14)
    - Bedient, Calvin, 1983-1990 (Box 14)
    - Bell, Marvin, 1971-1973 (Box 14)
    - Berg, Steven - American Poetry Review, circa 1980s-1990s; 6 folders (Box 14)
    - Burch, Eva, circa 1978 (Box 14)
    - Campana, Joseph A., Jr., circa 2005 (Box 14)
    - "Contracts", circa 1980s-1990s (Box 14)
    - Dobyns, Stephen, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 14)
    - Fan mail / requests for criticism, circa 2005 (Box 14)
    - Gardner, Tom - interview request, circa 1988 (Box 14)
    - Gargan, Carol, circa 1977-1979; 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Gibson, Tom, circa 1972 (Box 14)
    - Gilligan, Michael, circa 1975 (Box 14)
    - Hertz, Charles, circa 1968, 1993 (Box 14)
    - Hill, Diane E. - dreams, 1989 (Box 14)
    - Hillman, Brenda, 1980s; 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Kennerly, Karen, circa 1976 (Box 15)
    - Koestenbaum, Phyllis, circa 1989-1992 (Box 15)
    - Kunitz, Stanley, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 15)
    - "Letter and poems from Lorrie", undated (Box 15)
    - "MFA / Historical", circa 1977 (Box 15)
    - "MFA program evaluations", circa 1982 (Box 15)
    - Monley, Keith, 1970s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Moss, Sylvia, undated (Box 15)
    - [Murphy, Kay?], circa 1977 (Box 15)
    - Pinsky, Robert, 1982, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - "Rocio", undated (Box 15)
    - Ryan, Michael, circa 1975-1981; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Seidman, Hugh, 1970s-1990s (Box 15)
    - Simic, Charles, 1989 (Box 15)
    - Simons, Michelle - personal, 1980s (Box 15)
    - Voigt, Ellen Bryant, 1970s-1990s (Box 15)
    - Williams, C. K., 1995 (Box 15)
    - Winters, Rita A. - MFA semester study plan, circa 1977 (Box 15)
    - Winters, Rita A. - student, undated (Box 15)
  - Family correspondence, 1950s-2000s
    - Correspondence to parents, two notebooks, circa 1950s-1960s; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Glück family, 1960s-1970s; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - "Letters from L.G.", 1960s-1990s; 5 folders (Box 16)
    - "Letters from", undated (Box 16)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1950s-2000s
    - Unsorted correspondence and other papers, circa 1970s-2004; 17 folders (Box 17)
    - Unsorted correspondence and other papers, circa 1961-1996; 15 folders (Box 18)
    - Unsorted correspondence and other papers, circa 1956-2000s; 15 folders (Box 19)
- Writings, 1950s-2006; Series II; 9.33; (10 boxes)
  - Alphabetical writings, 1950s-2006
    - Achilles, circa 1985; 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Annotated poems, undated; 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Ararat, undated; 5 folders (Box 20)
    - Averno, circa 2006; 11 folders (Box 20)
    - Averno, circa 2006; 8 folders (Box 21)
    - "Book 5", undated; 3 folders (Box 21)
    - "Clear Morning from The Wild Iris, p.7", undated (Box 21)
    - "Copies - Heaven and Earth," poems, undated (Box 21)
    - "Copies of ret. poems", undated (Box 21)
    - "Daises" and other poems", undated (Box 21)
    - Descending Figure, circa 1980; 2 folders (Box 21)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes photograph.
    - Descending Figure with Lullaby," sheetmusic, 1986 (Box 25)
    - The Dream of Mourning, undated (Box 21)
    - "Early Iris", undated (Box 21)
    - "Early poems", circa 1965-1966; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - "Early poems and lines", circa 1950s-1960s (Box 21)
      Includes reviews and responses.
    - Firstborn article and poems, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 21)
    - "Friends poems", circa 1970s (Box 21)
    - "Goddard Poetry Colloquium" and "The Murderess", undated (Box 21)
    - "The Happy Heart - Wild Iris", undated; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - The House on Marshland, typescript, 1974 (Box 22)
    - "Ithica from Meadowlands P.12", undated (Box 22)
    - El Lirio Silvestre (Wild Iris), circa 1992 (Box 22)
    - "Louise", undated (Box 22)
    - "MFA writing program", undated (Box 22)
    - "Poems - Marshland", circa 1975 (Box 22)
    - Meadlowlands, circa 1997; 5 folders (Box 22)
    - "My Birthplace," typescript, undated (Box 22)
    - "New poems", undated (Box 22)
    - "Night Migrations", undated (Box 22)
    - "No Go", circa 1970s (Box 22)
    - "Nocturne Lamentations: Descending Figure", 1981 (Box 22)
    - "Noodle Junction," typescript, undated (Box 22)
    - "Old editions", circa 1962 (Box 22)
    - "On Night Song," "Disruption, Hesitation, Silence" and other poems, undated (Box 22)
    - "Pagan / Mt. Sinai - Book 5", undated (Box 22)
    - "Proofs and theories", undated (Box 22)
    - "Prose", undated (Box 22)
    - Red workbook, containing poems, correspondence and other material, circa 1980 (Box 22)
    - "A Romance" and other writings, undated (Box 22)
    - School papers, 1960s (Box 22)
    - The Seven Ages, circa 2001; 22 folders (Box 23)
    - "Stetson - L. Glück", undated (Box 24)
    - "Stories", various publishing letters, 1960s-1990s (Box 24)
    - "Talk", typescript sent to Beatrice Glück, 1989 (Box 24)
    - "Trillium, from The Wild Iris, pg. 4", circa 1992 (Box 24)
    - Vita Nova, circa 1997-1999; 6 folders (Box 24)
    - "Vita Nova," and "The Seven Ages", undated (Box 24)
    - The Wild Iris, circa 1992; 4 folders (Box 24)
    - "Xerox," poems, undated (Box 24)
    - "Xerox - 15 copies each," poems, undated (Box 24)
    - "Xerox copies - Vita story", undated (Box 24)
    - Yellow binder, poems, undated (Box 24)
      Contains plant pressing.
  - Notebooks, 1957-1960s
    - School notebooks, circa 1957-1959; 2 folders (Box 26)
    - School notebooks, circa 1960; 3 folders (Box 27)
    - Notebooks, 1950s-1960s; 7 folders (Box 27)
      Contains plant pressings.
    - Poetry quotes, homemade booklet, undated (Box 27)
    - Binder notebook, undated (Box 27)
  - Unsorted writings, 1960s-2000s
    - Unsorted writings and other papers, circa 1960s-2000s; 33 folders (Box 28)
    - Unsorted writings and other papers, circa 1960s-2000s; 15 folders (Box 29)
- Writings of others, 1970s-2005; Series III; 7.42; (8 boxes)
  - Bailey, Michele - 1998 State Poet Selection, binder (Box 30)
  - Ball, Sally - "From Their Windows", undated (Box 30)
  - Ball, Sara - poems, undated (Box 30)
  - Baxter, Charles - "Poor Devil", undated (Box 30)
  - [Benton, Lee Hampton?] - poems, undated; 2 folders (Box 30)
    Contains typescript of "Two Trees," by Ellen Bryant Voigt.
  - Berg, Stephen - poems, 1990s-2000s; 7 folders (Box 30)
    Contains "From Rimbaud," "Halo," "Oblivion," and various poems.
  - Bidart, Frank - poems, undated; 35 folders (Box 30)
    Contains "Desire," "For Bill Nestrick (1941-96)," "For the Twentieth Century," "Heart Beat," "Legacy," "Luggage," "Music Like Dirt," "The Poem is a Viel," "The Second Hour of the Night," "Star Dust," and other poems. Also contains correspondence and interviews.
  - Bidart, Frank - poems, undated; 16 folders (Box 31)
    Contains "Watching the Spring Festival," and "You Didn't Write, You Rewrote".
  - Brown, Stephanie - "Allegory of the Supermarket", undated (Box 32)
  - Campana, Joseph - "On Not Defending Poetry," and "Seraphic Monlogues", circa 2005; 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Campbell, Mary Baine - "Trouble", undated (Box 32)
  - Chaisson, Dan - "Coda: The Poet," and "Natural History", circa 2004; 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Clarke, Kevin Jefery - "The World in Front of Us", undated (Box 32)
  - Convisser, Julie - "The Tooth from the Shell", 1991 (Box 32)
  - Davis, Kathryn - writings, circa 1990s-2000s; 15 folders (Box 32)
    Contains "The Girl who Trod on a Loaf," "The Thin Place," "Versailles," and "The Walking Tour".
  - Davis, Kathryn - "The Walking Tour", circa 1999; 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Derry, Alice - "MFA writing program", circa 1980 (Box 33)
  - Dobyns, Stephan - poems, circa 1988; 3 folders (Box 33)
  - Fisher, Jessica - poems, circa 2006; 3 folders (Box 33)
  - Fletcher, Luellen - "Honor's Thesis in English", circa 1979 (Box 33)
  - Forché, Carolyn - "Two poems", circa 2000 (Box 33)
  - Gildroy, Doreen - "The Little Field of Self", undated (Box 33)
  - Gillett, Michelle - "MFA program for writers", circa 1981 (Box 33)
  - Goldensohn, Lorrie - "Occupying Forces", circa 1994 (Box 33)
  - Graham, Jorie - poems, undated; 3 folders (Box 33)
    Contains "Materialism," and "Tourists."
  - Halliday, Lisa - "Stump Louie", undated (Box 33)
  - Hopler, Jay - poems, circa 2005; 8 folders (Box 33)
    Contains "Green Squall," and other poems.
  - Huyler, Frank - "The Mercury Cure", circa 1994 (Box 33)
  - Kaufman, Debra - "Debra - Sysiphus", circa 1980 (Box 34)
  - Kaufman, Debra Nystrom - "MFA writing program", circa 1980 (Box 34)
  - Kennerly, Karen - "Invention of Tourism", circa 1998 (Box 34)
  - Kitchen, Judith - "The Woods Around it", photocopies, 1993 (Box 34)
  - Kunitz, Stanley - "King of the River", undated (Box 34)
  - Levin, Dana - poems, undated; 8 folders (Box 34)
    Contains "Bridge of Light," "Glass Book," "Heroics of Style," "In the Surgical Theatre," and other poems.
  - Lewis, Nancy Sherman - "MFA writing program evaluation", circa 1979 (Box 34)
  - Longenbach, James - writings, circa 2005; 6 folders (Box 34)
    Contains "Allegory," "Draft of a Letter," "The Hours of the Night," "Loggernaut reading series - Summer 2005," "Route," "Undiscovered Country," and other writings.
  - Margulies, [Donald?] - "Regarding Ellen Pinsky", undated (Box 34)
  - McDowell, Michael McEachern - memorial pamphlet, 1999 (Box 34)
  - McMichael, James - "Setting is the Chance", circa 1992 (Box 34)
  - Middleton, Anne - "Memories of Bill Nestrick", 2000 (Box 34)
  - Muske-Dukes, Carol - "Epitaph: A Novel", undated (Box 34)
  - Nealon, Chris - "Adultery", circa 1991 (Box 34)
  - Nystrom, Debra - "A Quarter Turn", circa 1990 (Box 34)
  - Pecor, Claudia Amanda - "Tea Leaves and Dark Water", undated (Box 34)
  - Pinsky, Ellen - writings, circa 1990s-2000s; 7 folders (Box 34)
    Contains "Sitcome Verité," "American Culture and the Voice of Poetry," and "Mortal Gifts".
  - Pinsky, Robert - writings, circa 1990s-2000s; 42 folders (Box 35)
    Contains "At the Worcester Museum," "A Book of Odes," "A Brief Guide to the Sounds of Poetry in English," "A Dialogue Between Poetry and Grief," "Invitation to Poetry," "The Game," "First Things to Hand," "Gulf Music," "Isolt," "Jersey Rain," material regarding King David, "Knight's Prayer," "Samurai Song," various lecture material, and essays.
  - Pinsky, Robert - writings, circa 1990s-2000s; 17 folders (Box 36)
    Contains "The Life of David," "Machine," "Chorus," "Ode to Meaning," "Rhythm and Measure in Spaces," "Stamford Address," "Vessel," "Porch Steps," "The Want Bone," miscellaneous poems, writings, and translations.
  - Raab, Lawrence - "Permanence", circa 1997; 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Rankine, Claudia - "Nothing In Nature is Private", undated (Box 36)
  - Reece, Spencer - "The Clerk's Tale", circa 2003; 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Reynolds, Gay - poems and correspondence, undated (Box 36)
  - Rhodes, Martha - poems, circa 1990s; 2 folders (Box 36)
    Contains "At the Gate," and "Perfect Disapperance".
  - Rosenberg, David - "Congregation: Contemporary Writers Read the Jewish Bible", circa 2000 (Box 36)
  - Rose, Rachel - poems, circa 1991-1994; 2 folders (Box 36)
    Contains "Archipelago," and "Bright Kingdom".
  - Ryan, Michael - poems, circa 1978; 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Selinger, Eric - "It Meant I Loved: Louise Gluck's Ararat", circa 1993 (Box 36)
  - Shore, Jane - "Music Minus One", undated (Box 36)
  - Siken, Richard - poems, circa 2000s; 4 folders (Box 36)
    Contains "Crush," and "Litany in which Certain Things are Crossed Out".
  - Slate, Ron - "The Incentive of the Maggot", undated (Box 36)
  - Steckel, Christine - MFA program, circa 1981; 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Stewart, Stephanie - "A Reckoning", circa 1998-2000; 5 folders (Box 36)
  - Stockwell, Samn - "Recital", undated (Box 37)
  - Streckfus, Peter - "The Cuckoo", undated; 3 folders (Box 37)
  - Theoharis, Theoharis C. - "Cavafy Poems", circa 1998 (Box 37)
  - Ungerer, Kathryn - "Eternity", undated (Box 37)
  - Vincent, John - "Prick", circa 2000 (Box 37)
  - Voigt, Ellen Bryant - poems, undated; 7 folders (Box 37)
    Contains "The Art of Distance," annotated poems, "The Feeder," "The Forces of Plenty," "Messenger" reviews, "Song and Story," and various other works.
  - Weiner, Joshua - "From the World's Room: Poems", circa 2001 (Box 37)
  - Wenderoth, Joe - "Disfortune", undated (Box 37)
  - Williams, C. K. - poems, circa 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 37)
    Contains "Repair".
  - "The Prodigal Son", unknown author, undated (Box 37)
  - "Regarding Streckfus" notes, undated (Box 37)
  - "Therapist Play", unknown author, undated (Box 37)
- Other papers, 1950s-1990s; Series IV; 1; (1 box)
  - Ephemera, 1991, undated
    - National Portrait Gallery bookmark, undated (Box 38)
    - Drivers License and DMV material, 1991 (Box 38)
    - Key, undated (Box 38)
    - Flatware knife, undated (Box 38)
  - Photographs, 1950s-1990s
    - Northfield photographs, circa 1960s (Box 38)
    - "Misc.," photographs with printed material, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 38)
    - Photographs of Louise Glück, 1950s-1980s (Box 38)
    - Photographs with negatives, circa 1990s (Box 38)
    - Glück - Northfield photographs, circa 1970s (Box 38)
- Artwork, 1958-1965, undated; Series V; 7.67; (5 boxes) + 8 art
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, oil on canvas, undated (Box 1 (Art))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, oil on canvas, 1965 (Box 2 (Art))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, oil on canvas, 1959 (Box 3 (Art))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, oil on canvas, 1963 (Box 4 (Art))
  - Nude with Blond Hair, by Louise Glück, oil on canvas, 1963 (Box 5 (Art))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, oil on canvas, 1958 (Box 6 (Art))
  - Portrait of Louise Glück, by Monte Goerner, pastel, 1963 (Box 7 (Art))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, watercolor and pastel, 1962 (Box 8 (Oversize))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, watercolor and pastel, 1965 (Box 9 (Oversize))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, watercolor and pastel, 1962 (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - Untitled drawing, by Louise Glück, pencil, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, watercolor and pastel, 1962 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Untitled, by Louise Glück, oil on canvas, 1961 (Box 13 (Art))
- Restricted material, Series VI; 1; (1 box) (Box 39)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until 2050. For further information consult the appropriate curator.